I'm an ecologist,
أنا خبير بيئي
mostly a coral reef ecologist.
خبير شعب مرجانية في المقام الاول
I started out in Chesapeake Bay
كانت بداياتي في خليج تشسبيك
and went diving in the winter
وذهبت للغوص في الشتاء
and became a tropical ecologist overnight.
وأصبحت خبيرا بالبيئة الإستوائية بين عشية وضحاها.
And it was really a lot of fun
وكانت حقا ممتعه جدا
for about 10 years.
لمدة عشر سنوات
I mean, somebody pays you
أعني , أن أحدا ما يدفع لك المال
to go around and travel
من أجل التجول والترحال
and look at some of the most
وانظر الى بعض الاماكن
beautiful places on the planet.
الجميلة على كوكب الارض
And that was what I did.
و هذ كل ماقمت به
And I ended up in Jamaica,
وانتهى بي المطاف في جامايكا
in the West Indies,
في الهند الغربية
where the coral reefs were really
حيث كانت الشعب المرجانية حقا
among the most extraordinary, structurally,
وسط الاكثر روعه والاكثر عمرانا
that I ever saw in my life.
التي لم اشاهد مثلها طيلة حياتي
And this picture here,
وهذه الصور هنا
it's really interesting, it shows two things:
مثيرة للأهتمام حقا ,تظهر شيئين اثنين
First of all, it's in black and white
أولا , هي ذو لون أسود ولون أبيض
because the water was so clear
وذلك بسبب أن الماء كان شديد الصفاء
and you could see so far,
ويمكنك أن ترى من بعيد
and film was so slow
والفلم كان بطيء جدا
in the 1960s and early 70s,
في نهاية الستينات وبداية السبعينات
you took pictures in black and white.
صورت باللون الأسود والابيض
The other thing it shows you
الشيء الآخر تظهرك
is that, although there's this beautiful
وبالرغم من ذلك توجد هذه
forest of coral,
الغابه الجميلة من المرجان
there are no fish in that picture.
لايوجد سمك في الصورة
Those reefs at Discovery Bay, Jamaica
تلك الشعب في خليج جمايكا المكتشف
were the most studied coral reefs
أكثر الشعب المرجانية دراسة
in the world for 20 years.
في العالم منذ 20 عام
We were the best and the brightest.
نحن كنا الافضل والأبرع
People came to study our reefs from Australia,
يأتون الناس لدراسة شعبنا المرجانية من استراليا
which is sort of funny
التي مضحكة نوعا ما
because now we go to theirs.
لأننا الان نذهب لبيئاتهم
And the view of scientists
ووجهة نظر العلماء
about how coral reefs work, how they ought to be,
عن كيفية عيش الشعب المرجانية, كيف يجب أن تكون
was based on these reefs
كانت تعتمد على هذه الشعب
without any fish.
من دون الأسماك
Then, in 1980,
وبعد حين ,وفي عام 1980
there was a hurricane, Hurricane Allen.
كان هناك إعصار مداري
I put half the lab
وضعت نصف المختبر
up in my house.
بسرعه في منزلي
The wind blew very strong.
عصفت الريح بشكل قوي جدا
The waves were 25
وصلت موجات البحر 25 لـ
to 50 feet high.
50 قدم فوق سطح البحر
And the reefs disappeared, and new islands formed,
وأختفت الشعب , وتكونت جزيرة جديدة
and we thought, "Well, we're real smart.
وفكرنا , حسنا نحن اذكياء حقا
We know that hurricanes
نحن نعلم ان الاعاصير
have always happened in the past."
لطالما حدثت في الماضي
And we published a paper in Science,
وأصدرنا صحيفة علمية
the first time that anybody ever
هي المرة الأولى التي لم يسبق لأحد
described the destruction
أن وصف الدمار
on a coral reef by a major hurricane.
في الشعب المرجانية من خلال اعصار عظيم
And we predicted what would happen,
ولقد توقعنا مالذي يمكن أن يحدث
and we got it all wrong.
وفهمناه بشكل خاطئ
And the reason was
والعله كانت
because of overfishing,
بسبب الأفراط في صيد السمك
and the fact that a last common grazer,
والحقيقة هي أن آخر آكلات الأعشاب الشائعة,
a sea urchin, died.
وهو قنفذ البحر قد مات
And within a few months
وبعد أشهر قليلة
after that sea urchin dying, the seaweed started to grow.
وبعد أن ينقرض قنفذ البحر, تبدأ الطحالب بالنمو
And that is the same reef;
وتلك هي نفس الشعب
that's the same reef 15 years ago;
وهذه هي نفس الشعب منذ 15 عام
that's the same reef today.
وهي نفس الشعب اليوم
The coral reefs of the north coast of Jamaica
الشعب المرجانية لساحل جمايكا الشمالي
have a few percent live coral cover
لديه اجزاء من المئة غطاء مرجاني
and a lot of seaweed and slime.
والكثير من الطحالب والطين
And that's more or less the story
وهذه القصة الى حد قريب
of the coral reefs of the Caribbean,
لشعب جزر الكاريبي المرجانية
and increasingly, tragically,
وبشكل متزايد ومأساوي
the coral reefs worldwide.
الشعب المرجانية أصبحت منتشرة عالميا
Now, that's my little, depressing story.
والآن هذه قصتي الكئيبة القصيرة
All of us in our 60s and 70s
جميعنا في الستينات والسبعينات
have comparable depressing stories.
لدينا قصص كئيبة متشابهه
There are tens of thousands
لدينا العشرات من الألوف
of those stories out there,
من هذه القصص المعلنة
and it's really hard to conjure up
ومن الصعب ان تستحضر الذاكرة
much of a sense of well-being,
الكثير من معنى الصحة والعافية
because it just keeps getting worse.
وذلك بسبب أن الأمور تزداد سوء
And the reason it keeps getting worse
والسبب أن الأمور تزداد سوءا
is that after a natural catastrophe,
هو مابعد الكارثة الطبيعيه
like a hurricane,
مثل الإعصار
it used to be that there was
من المعتاد أن يكون
some kind of successional sequence of recovery,
نوعا من السلسلة المتتابعة من الشفاء
but what's going on now is that
لكن مايحدثث الآن هو
overfishing and pollution and climate change
الأفراط في صيد الأسماك والتلوث و وتغير المناخ
are all interacting
جميعها تتفاعل
in a way that prevents that.
بطريقة تمنع ذلك
And so I'm going to sort of go through
وأنا ايضا سوف اصنف ما أنجزته
and talk about those three
وأتحدث عن هذه الثلاثة
kinds of things.
أنواع من الأشياء
We hear a lot about
نسمع الكثير عن
the collapse of cod.
عن تقلص سمك القد
It's difficult to imagine that
من الصعب تصور ذلك
two, or some historians would say three world wars
اثنان أو بعضا من المؤرخين سوف يقولون ثلاث حروب عالمية
were fought during the colonial era
حاربت خلال العصر الإستعماري
for the control of cod.
من أجل التحكم في سمك القد
Cod fed most of the people of Western Europe.
سمك القد اطعم اغلب اوروبا الغربية
It fed the slaves
أطعمت العبيد
brought to the Antilles,
احضرت الى الجزر الهندية
the song "Jamaica Farewell" --
اغنية "وداعا جمايكا"
"Ackee rice salt fish are nice" --
آكي السمك المالح مع الرز لذيذ
is an emblem of the importance
هو شعار الأهمية
of salt cod from northeastern Canada.
لسمك القد من شمال شرقي كندا
It all collapsed in the 80s and the 90s:
دمر كليا في الثمانينات والتسعينيات
35,000 people lost their jobs.
35 الف شخص فقدوا وظائفهم
And that was the beginning
وهذه كانت البداية
of a kind of serial depletion
لباب مسلسل الاستنزاف
from bigger and tastier species
من أكبر واكثر جاذبية من الأصناف
to smaller and not-so-tasty species,
الى أصغر وغير جذاب من الاصناف
from species that were near to home
من الأصناف التي كانت قريبة من المنزل
to species that were all around the world,
الى الأصناف التي كانت حول العالم
and what have you.
والذي تمكله انت
It's a little hard to understand that,
من الصعب أن تفهم ذلك
because you can go to a Costco in the United States
لانك تستطيع ان تذهب ال كوستكو في الولايات المتحده
and buy cheap fish.
وتشتري سمك رخيص
You ought to read the label to find out where it came from,
ينبغي عليك أن تقرأ الملصق لتكتشف من أين جائت
but it's still cheap,
لكنها تبقى رخيصه
and everybody thinks it's okay.
والجميع يظن انها جيده
It's hard to communicate this,
ومن الصعب أن تتواصل معها
and one way that I think is really interesting
ولذلك هناك طريقه واحدة التي اعتقد انها مثيرة للاهتمام
is to talk about sport fish,
هو أن تتحدث عن رياضة السمك
because people like to go out and catch fish.
لان الناس يحبون الذهاب للتنزه وصيد السمك
It's one of those things.
هذه واحدة من عدة اشياء
This picture here shows the trophy fish,
هذه الصورة تظهر عرض السمك
the biggest fish caught
صيد السمك الاكبر
by people who pay a lot of money
من قبل اناس يدفعون الكثير من المال
to get on a boat,
لركوب القارب
go to a place off of Key West in Florida,
انصرف الى مكان من مفتاح غرب فلوريدا
drink a lot of beer,
واشرب المزيد من الجعه
throw a lot of hooks and lines into the water,
وارمي الكثير من صنارة الصيد والخيوط في البحر
come back with the biggest and the best fish,
وأرجع بالسمك الأفضل والأكبر
and the champion trophy fish
وبطل نصب تذكار السمك
are put on this board, where people take a picture,
توضع في السفينة , عند المكان الذي يصور فيه الناس
and this guy is obviously
وهذا الشاب يبدو
really excited about that fish.
متشوقا حقا عن السمك
Well, that's what it's like now,
حسنا ,هذا مايبدو عليه الآن
but this is what it was like in the 1950s
لكن هذا ماكان يبدو في عام 1950
from the same boat in the same place
من نفس القارب في نفس المكان
on the same board on the same dock.
في نفس السفينة في نفس حوض السفينة
The trophy fish
ونفس عرض تذكار السمك
were so big
والذي كان كبيرا جدا
that you couldn't put any of those small fish up on it.
لهذا السبب لا تستطيع أن تضع السمك الصغير عليه
And the average size trophy fish
ومتوسط حجم السمك المعروض
weighed 250 to 300 pounds, goliath grouper,
يزن من250 الى 300 باوند
and if you wanted to go out and kill something,
واذا أردت الذهاب و تقتل شيء ما
you could pretty much count on
يمكنك جدا الإعتماد
being able to catch one of those fish.
أن تكون قادرا على صيد واحده من تلك الأسماك
And they tasted really good.
وطعمها حقا جيد
And people paid less in 1950 dollars
والناس يدفعون أقل الدولارات في عام 1950
to catch that
لصيدها
than what people pay now
أكثر مما يدفع الناس الآن
to catch those little, tiny fish.
لأمساك هذه الاسماك الضئيلة الصغيرة
And that's everywhere.
وهذا في كل مكان
It's not just the fish, though,
وهومع ذلك ليس السمك فقط
that are disappearing.
هي يختفون
Industrial fishing uses big stuff,
يستخدم الصيد الصناعي ادوات كبيرة
big machinery.
الات كبيرة
We use nets that are 20 miles long.
نحن نستخدم شبكات بطول 20 ميل
We use longlines
نستخدم خطوط طويلة
that have one million or two million hooks.
والتي تمتلك مليون او مليونين صنارة صيد
And we trawl,
ونحن نصيد بالشبكة
which means to take something
والتي تعني أن تمسك بشيء ما
the size of a tractor trailer truck
حجم مقطورة الشاحنة
that weighs thousands and thousands of pounds,
والتي تزن الألوف والألوف من الباوندات
put it on a big chain,
تضعها في سلسلة كبيرة
and drag it across the sea floor
وتسحبها نحو سطح البحر
to stir up the bottom and catch the fish.
لأجل تحريك الأسفل وصيد السمك
Think of it as
وفكر بها على أن
being kind of the bulldozing of a city
تكون تحفير لمدينة
or of a forest,
أو لغابة
because it clears it away.
وذلك بسبب ترتيبها
And the habitat destruction
ودمار الموطن الطبيعي
is unbelievable.
لايمكن تصدقيه
This is a photograph,
وهذه صوره
a typical photograph,
صورة طبيعية
of what the continental shelves
لشكل المخزون القاري
of the world look like.
للعالم
You can see the rows in the bottom,
تستطيع أن ترى أعماق الأسفل
the way you can see the rows
الطريقة الي ترى بها الأعماق
in a field that has just been plowed
في الحقل الذي تم حرثه للتو
to plant corn.
لزرع القمح
What that was, was a forest of sponges and coral,
ماذا كانت, كانت غابة من حيوان الأسفنج والمرجان
which is a critical habitat
والتي كانت مسكن شديد الأهمية
for the development of fish.
من أجل نمو السمك
What it is now is mud,
ماهو عليه الآن هو طين
and the area of the ocean floor
ومنطقة سطح المحيط
that has been transformed from forest
التي تم تحويلها من غابة إلى طين
to level mud, to parking lot,
الى طين متساوي
is equivalent to the entire area
مساوي للمنطقة كلها
of all the forests
لجميع الغابات
that have ever been cut down
تم قطع الاشجار كليا
on all of the earth
في جميع اقطار الأرض
in the history of humanity.
في تاريخ البشرية
We've managed to do that
ونجحنا في تحقيق ذلك
in the last 100 to 150 years.
في آخر 100 الى 150 عام
We tend to think of oil spills
نحن نتجه نحو التفكير بالزيت الطافي على سطح الماء
and mercury
والزئبق
and we hear a lot about plastic these days.
ونسمع الكثير عن البلاستيك هذه الأيام
And all of that stuff is really disgusting,
وكل هذه المواد هي مثيرة للاشمئزاز حقا
but what's really insidious
ولكن ماهو ماكر حقا
is the biological pollution that happens
هو التلوث البيولوجي الذي يحدث
because of the magnitude of the shifts
وذلك بسبب أهمية تغير الطقس
that it causes
الذي يسببه
to entire ecosystems.
للنظام البيئي ككل
And I'm going to just talk very briefly
وأنا سوف أتكلم بشكل مختصر جدا
about two kinds of biological pollution:
عن نوعين من التلوث الجرثومي
one is introduced species
الأول سوف يقدم بشكل مصنف
and the other is what comes from nutrients.
والآخر هو مايأتي من المادة الغذائية
So this is the infamous
وهذا هو المخز
Caulerpa taxifolia,
كاولربا تاكسيفوليا
the so-called killer algae.
وهذا ما يسمى الطحلب القاتل
A book was written about it.
يوجد كتاب مؤلف عنه
It's a bit of an embarrassment.
والكتاب محرج قليلا
It was accidentally released
وهو منشور من غير قصد
from the aquarium in Monaco,
من المربى المائي في موناكو
it was bred to be cold tolerant
تمت تربيتها حتى تكون ضعيفة متسامحة
to have in peoples aquaria.
لتملك في حوض الناس المائي
It's very pretty,
هي جميلة جدا
and it has rapidly started
ولديها بداية سريعة
to overgrow
لتنمو سريعا
the once very rich
في ما مضى غنية جدا
biodiversity of the
التنوع الحي في
northwestern Mediterranean.
شمال غربي البحر المتوسط
I don't know how many of you remember the movie
لا أعلم كم منكم يتذكر الفيلم
"The Little Shop of Horrors,"
محل الرعب الصغير
but this is the plant of "The Little Shop of Horrors."
ولكن هذه أرض محل الرعب الصغير
But, instead of devouring the people in the shop,
ولكن بدلا عن ابادة البشر في المحل
what it's doing is overgrowing
مالذي يفعله هو سرعة النمو
and smothering
وكثافة التغطية
virtually all of the bottom-dwelling life
واقعيا جميع الحياة الموجودة في قاع
of the entire northwestern
الشمال الغربي
Mediterranean Sea.
للبحر المتوسط
We don't know anything that eats it,
لانعلم أي شيء يأكل منه
we're trying to do all sorts of genetics
ونحاول أن ننتج جميع انواع الجينات
and figure out something that could be done,
ونكتشف شيء ما يمكن ان يكون المفعول
but, as it stands, it's the monster from hell,
ولكن حتى الآن لا يوجد حل ناجح
about which nobody knows what to do.
ولا أحد يعلم ماذا يعمل
Now another form of pollution
والآن شكل آخر للتلوث
that's biological pollution
وهو التلوث الجرثومي
is what happens from excess nutrients.
وهو ماينتج عن التدخل الغذائي
The green revolution,
الثورة الخضراء
all of this artificial nitrogen fertilizer, we use too much of it.
جميع نيتروجين السماد الصناعي, الذي نستخدمه بشكل كبير جدا
It's subsidized, which is one of the reasons we used too much of it.
هو مدعوم ماليا , وهو أحد الأسباب الذي جعلنا نستخدمه بشكل كبير جدا
It runs down the rivers,
يجري أسفل الأنهار
and it feeds the plankton,
ويغذي عوالق الكائنات الحية
the little microscopic plant cells
والخلايا النباتية المجهرية الصغيرة
in the coastal water.
في الماء الساحلي
But since we ate all the oysters
ولكن منذ أن أكلنا جميع المحارات
and we ate all the fish that would eat the plankton,
وأكلنا جميع الأسماك التي تأكل عوالق الكائنات الحية
there's nothing to eat the plankton
لن يوجد شي واحد ليأكل عوالق الكائنات الحية
and there's more and more of it,
وسيوجد الكثير والكثير منه
so it dies of old age,
هكذا ستموت بعد ان تعيش طويلا
which is unheard of for plankton.
والتي تكون مجهولة بالنسبة لعوالق الكائنات الحية
And when it dies, it falls to the bottom
وعندما تموت سوف تسقط في الأسفل
and then it rots,
ومن ثم تتعفن
which means that bacteria break it down.
وهذا يعني أن البكتيريا حللتها
And in the process
واثناء هذه العملية !!
they use up all the oxygen,
تستهلك كل الأكسجين
and in using up all the oxygen
وأثناء استهلاكها للأكسجين
they make the environment utterly lethal
سوف تجعل البيئة مميتة تماما
for anything that can't swim away.
لأي شيء لايستطيح السباحة
So, what we end up with
وهكذا سوف ينتهي بنا المطاف الى
is a microbial zoo
حديقة حيوانات جرثومية
dominated by bacteria
تسيطر عليها البكتيريا
and jellyfish, as you see
وقنديل البحر كما ترون
on the left in front of you.
امامكم يسارا
And the only fishery left --
ويبقى الصيد الوحيد
and it is a commercial fishery --
وصيد السمك التجاري
is the jellyfish fishery
هو صيد قنديل البحر
you see on the right, where there used to be prawns.
نرى في اليمين , حيث كان يوجد الروبيان
Even in Newfoundland
وحتى في نيو فاوندلاند
where we used to catch cod,
حيث اعتدنا على صيد سمك القد
we now have a jellyfish fishery.
نحن الان نصيد قنديل البحر
And another version of this sort of thing
ونسخة أخرى من هذا النوع
is what is often called red tides
هو مايطلق عليه المد الأحمر
or toxic blooms.
أو الزهرة السامة
That picture on the left is just staggering to me.
الصورة مذهلة بالنسبة لي
I have talked about it a million times,
وتحدثت عنها ملايين المرات
but it's unbelievable.
ولكن لايمكن تصديقه
In the upper right of that picture on the left
وفي اعلى اليمين من الصورة في اليسار
is almost the Mississippi Delta,
هو دلتا المسسبي تقريبا
and the lower left of that picture
وفي اسفل اليسار من تلك الصورة
is the Texas-Mexico border.
تكساس وحدود المكسيك
You're looking at the entire
انتم تنظرون الى كل
northwestern Gulf of Mexico;
شمال غرب خليج المكسيك
you're looking at one toxic
انتم تنظرون الى زهرة سامة واحدة
dinoflagellate bloom that can kill fish,
التي من الممكن أن تقتل السمك
made by that beautiful little creature
بفعل هذا الكائن الحي الصغير الجميل
on the lower right.
في أسفل اليمين
And in the upper right you see this
وفي أعلى اليمين ترى هذا
black sort of cloud
الشئ الاسود نوع من السحابة
moving ashore.
تتحرك نحو الساحل
That's the same species.
وتلك هي نفس الصنف
And as it comes to shore and the wind blows,
وبينما هي تتجه الى الساحل . والرياح تهب
and little droplets of the water get into the air,
وقطرات صغيرة من الماء تصعد الى الهواء
the emergency rooms of all the hospitals fill up
غرفة الطوارئ في جميع المستشفيات تمتلئ
with people with acute respiratory distress.
بالناس المصابين بأزمات تنفسية حادة
And that's retirement homes
وهذه بيوت العزل
on the west coast of Florida.
في الساحل الغربي من فلوريدا
A friend and I did this thing in Hollywood
صديق وأنا فعلنا هذا الشيء في هوليوود
we called Hollywood ocean night,
وسميناه ليلة محيط هوليوود
and I was trying to figure out how to
وحاولت أن اكتشف كيف أن
explain to actors what's going on.
أشرح للمثلين ماذا يحدث
And I said,
و قلت
"So, imagine you're in a movie called 'Escape from Malibu'
اذن تخيلوا أنكم في فلم يدعى " الهروب من ماليبوا
because all the beautiful people have moved
وذلك بسبب أن جميع الأشخاص اللطيفين انتقلوا
to North Dakota, where it's clean and safe.
الى شمال داكوتا ,حيث انه مكان نظيف وآمن
And the only people who are left there
والأشخاص الذي بقوا
are the people who can't afford
هم الأشخاص الذين لم يتحملوا تكلفة
to move away from the coast,
أن يرتحلوا من الساحل
because the coast, instead of being paradise,
وذلك بسبب أن الساحل, بدلا أن يكون نعيما
is harmful to your health."
اصبح له ضرر على صحتكم
And then this is amazing.
وبعد ذلك هذا هو مدهش
It was when I was on holiday last early autumn in France.
كان عندما كنت في إجازة في بداية الخريف الماضي في فرنسا
This is from the coast of Brittany,
من بريتني الساحلي
which is being enveloped
والذي أصبح مغطى
in this green, algal slime.
بهذه الخضرة وحل الطحلب
The reason that it attracted so much attention,
ويكمن السبب في أنها تجذب الانتباه جدا
besides the fact that it's disgusting,
بجانب أنها مقززة
is that sea birds flying over it
هو اثناء تحليق طيور البحر فوقها
are asphyxiated by the smell and die,
تصاب بالأختناق بسبب الرائحة وتموت
and a farmer died of it,
والمزارع يتحرق شوقا له
and you can imagine the scandal that happened.
ويمكن أن تتخيل العار الذي يحدث
And so there's this war
وهكذا يوجد هذا العداء
between the farmers
بين المزارعين
and the fishermen about it all,
والصيادين بشأنه
and the net result is that
والنتيجة الصافية هو أن
the beaches of Brittany have to be bulldozed of this stuff
شواطئ بريتني يجب أن تدمر لهذا الغرض
on a regular basis.
بشكل منتظم
And then, of course, there's climate change,
وبعد ذلك سيوجد تغير المناخ بالطبع
and we all know about climate change.
ونحن نعلم جميعا عن تغير المناخ
I guess the iconic figure of it
من ناحية الظواهر الكبيرة أظن
is the melting of the ice
وهي ذوبان الثلوج
in the Arctic Sea.
في القطب الشمالي
Think about the thousands and thousands of people who died
فكر بالآف والآف من الناس الذين ماتو
trying to find the Northwest Passage.
وهم يحاولون أن يجدوا طريق الشمال الغربي
Well, the Northwest Passage is already there.
حسنا , الشمالي الغربي موجود مسبقا
I think it's sort of funny;
أعتقد انه ممتع نوعا ما
it's on the Siberian coast,
انه في ساحل سيبيريا
maybe the Russians will charge tolls.
وربما الروس سيضعون الرسوم
The governments of the world
وحكومات العالم
are taking this really seriously.
يأخذون هذا على محمل الجد
The military of the Arctic nations
وشعب القطب الشمالي العسكري
is taking it really seriously.
يأخذ هذا على محمل الجد
For all the denial of climate change
لجميع منكري تغير المناخ
by government leaders,
من رؤساء الحكومات
the CIA
و وكالة الاستخبارات الأمريكية
and the navies of Norway
وأسطول البحرية النرويجي
and the U.S. and Canada, whatever
والولايات المتحدة وكندا , أي كان
are busily thinking about
منشغلين بالتفكير في
how they will secure their territory
كيف سيحمون مناطقهم
in this inevitability
من هذا القدر المحتوم
from their point of view.
من وجهة نظرهم
And, of course, Arctic communities are toast.
ومجتمعات القطب الشمالي خاصة
The other kinds of effects of climate change --
والعناصر المؤثرة الاخرى على تغير المناخ
this is coral bleaching. It's a beautiful picture, right?
هذه هى الشعب البيضاء. و هى صورة جميلة اليس كذلك.
All that white coral.
وجميعها مرجان أبيض
Except it's supposed to be brown.
ماعدا انها يفترض أن تكون بنيه
What happens is that
وماذا حدث هو أن ذلك
the corals are a symbiosis,
المرجان متكافل
and they have these little algal cells
ولديها تلك الخلايا الطحلبية الصغيرة
that live inside them.
التي تعيش بداخلهم
And the algae give the corals sugar,
والطحلب يزود المرجان بالسكر
and the corals give the algae
والمرجان يزود الطحلب
nutrients and protection.
بالمادة الغذائية والبروتين
But when it gets too hot,
ولكن عندما تزداد حرارتها
the algae can't make the sugar.
الطحلب لايمكن أن يتحول لسكر
The corals say, "You cheated. You didn't pay your rent."
المرجان يقول , لقد خدعتني لم تقم بدفع الايجار
They kick them out, and then they die.
فيقوم بطردهم وبذلك يموتوا
Not all of them die; some of them survive,
وليس جميعهم يموتون , فبعضهم ينجوا
some more are surviving,
والمزيد ينجوا
but it's really bad news.
ولكنها أخبار سيئة
To try and give you a sense of this,
لكي أوضح لك الصورة
imagine you go camping in July
تخيل أنك ذاهب للتخييم في شهر يوليو
somewhere in Europe or in North America,
في بعض الأماكن في أمريكا الشمالية
and you wake up the next morning, and you look around you,
وتستقيظ في الصباح التالي , وتنظر حولك
and you see that 80 percent of the trees,
وترى 80 في المائة من الاشجار
as far as you can see,
بأقصى بعد يمكنك أن ترى
have dropped their leaves and are standing there naked.
اسقطت أوراقها وتقف عاريه
And you come home, and you discover
وعندما تأتي للمنزل , تكتشف أن
that 80 percent of all the trees
80 في المئة من الأشجار
in North America and in Europe
في أمريكا الشمالية وأوروبا
have dropped their leaves.
أسقطت أوراقها
And then you read in the paper a few weeks later,
وقبل أسابيع اقرأ في الصحف
"Oh, by the way, a quarter of those died."
بالمناسبة ربع هذه الأشجار تموت
Well, that's what happened in the Indian Ocean
حسنا هذا مايحدث في المحيط الهندي
during the 1998 El Nino,
خلال عام 1998 في النينو
an area vastly greater
في منطقة متسعة كبيرة
than the size of North America and Europe,
أكبر من حجم أمريكا الشمالية وأوروبا
when 80 percent of all the corals bleached
عندما يزال لون 80 في المئة من المرجان
and a quarter of them died.
وربعهم يموتون
And then the really scary thing
والشيء المخيف حقا
about all of this --
عن هذا كله
the overfishing, the pollution and the climate change --
الإفراط في الصيد, والتلوث , وتغير المناخ
is that each thing doesn't happen in a vacuum.
هو أن تلك الاشياء لاتحدث في فراغ
But there are these, what we call, positive feedbacks,
ولكن هناك تلك التي نسميها الدعم الإيجابي
the synergies among them
التعاون الذي بينهم
that make the whole vastly greater
يصنع كل الاتساع الكبير
than the sum of the parts.
اكثر من مجموع الاجزاء
And the great scientific challenge
والتحدي العلمي العظيم
for people like me in thinking about all this,
لاشخاص مثلي في التفكير في هذا كله
is do we know how
هو عمل نعلم كيف
to put Humpty Dumpty back together again?
أن نعيد تركيب الذي لايمكن اصلاحه
I mean, because we, at this point, we can protect it.
اقصد , وذلك بسبب أننا في هذه النقطه , نستطيع حمايته
But what does that mean?
ولكن ماذا يعني هذا ؟
We really don't know.
نحن لانعلم حقا
So what are the oceans going to be like
اذن كيف سيبدو شكل المحيط
in 20 or 50 years?
خلال 20 او 50 سنة ؟
Well, there won't be any fish
حسنا لن يوجد أي سمك
except for minnows,
ماعدا المنوة (سمك اوروبي )
and the water will be pretty dirty,
والماء سيكون متسخ جدا
and all those kinds of things
وجميع تلك الأشياء
and full of mercury, etc., etc.
ومليء بالزئبق , الى آخره , الى اخره
And dead zones will get bigger and bigger
ومركز المشكلة سوف يكبر ويكبر
and they'll start to merge,
وسوف يبدأون الدمج
and we can imagine something like
ونستطيع تخيل شيء مثل
the dead-zonification
مناطق الموت
of the global, coastal ocean.
في العالم , المحيط الساحلي
Then you sure won't want to eat fish that were raised in it,
وبعد ذلك ستكون متأكدا انك لاتريد أن تأكل من السمك الذي نما فيه
because it would be a kind of
لانه سيكون نوعا من
gastronomic Russian roulette.
بمثابة المواجهة الروسية بالمسدس (لعبة روسية مميتة يتبادل فيها رجلين إطلاق مسدس على رأسيهما لا توجد به إلا رصاصة واحدة )
Sometimes you have a toxic bloom;
واحيانا تتناول برعم سام
sometimes you don't.
واحيانا لا
That doesn't sell.
وذلك لا يباع
The really scary things though
هناك حقا اشياء مخيفة بالرغم من ذلك
are the physical, chemical,
جسدي وكيميائي
oceanographic things that are happening.
الصور داخل المحيط
As the surface of the ocean gets warmer,
بينما سطح المحيط يزيد حرارة
the water is lighter when it's warmer,
الماء يخف عندما يكون اكثر حراره
it becomes harder and harder
ويصبح اصعب واصعب
to turn the ocean over.
أن ينقلب المحيط
We say it becomes
نحن نقول , أنه يصبح
more strongly stratified.
أقوى تطابق
The consequence of that is that
ونتيجة لذلك هو
all those nutrients
جميع المواد الغذائية
that fuel the great anchoveta fisheries,
]دعم مهنة صيد السمك الكبيرة
of the sardines of California
لسمك الساردين في كالفورنيا
or in Peru or whatever,
او في البيرو أو اي كان
those slow down
انخفضت
and those fisheries collapse.
وانهارت مهنة صيد السمك
And, at the same time,
و في نفس الوقت
water from the surface, which is rich in oxygen,
وماء سطح البحر الغني بالاوكسجين
doesn't make it down
لن ينتجه
and the ocean turns into a desert.
والمحيط يتحول إلى صحراء
So the question is: How are we all
والسؤال هو :كيف جميعنا
going to respond to this?
سوف نستجيب لهذا ؟
And we can do
ونستطيع أن نعمل
all sorts of things to fix it,
جميع الأشياء لاصلاحها
but in the final analysis,
ولكن في التحليل الأخير
the thing we really need to fix
الاشياء التي نحتاج لاصلاحها حقا
is ourselves.
هي انفسنا
It's not about the fish; it's not about the pollution;
هي ليس عن السمك وليس عن التلوث
it's not about the climate change.
وليس عن تغير المناخ
It's about us
أنه عن انفسنا
and our greed and our need for growth
و جشعنا واحتياجاتنا من اجل الإزدهار
and our inability to imagine a world
وعجزنا عن تخيل العالم
that is different from the selfish world
والذي هو مختلف عن العالم الأناني
we live in today.
الذي نعيشه اليوم
So the question is: Will we respond to this or not?
اذن السؤال هو هل سنستجيب لهذا أم لا ؟
I would say that the future of life
أود أن أقول مستقبل الحياة
and the dignity of human beings
وكرامة البشرية
depends on our doing that.
تعتمد على اعمالنا تلك
Thank you. (Applause)
شكرا لكم ترجمة ( أحمد العنزي)®™